Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Okay, today's daf דף daf is
daf tet vav דף טו daf tet vav and we pick up
in the middle of yud daled amud bet יד עמוד ב yud
daled amud bet because we had mentioned in the mishna משנה mishna
dividing up various scrolls of Tanakh תנ"ך Tanakh when a larger discussion
about the scrolls of Tanakh תנ"ך, Tanakh, both the physical ones and
basically the questions
about them as belonging in the Tanakh תנ"ך Tanakh and their authorship
and so on, which is what we're going to actually transition to.
Okay, so yesterday we had a whole fascinating discussion about what the
size of a classic Sefer Torah ספר תורה Sefer Torah would look
like, what it looked like in the aron ארון, aron, my whole
point about how the connection being made between the luchot לוחות luchot
and the aron ארון, aron, which is super inaccessible, only to the
Kohen Gadol כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on Yom Kippur יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, and then the connecting of the dots to that to a
Sefer Torah ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, which is fully accessible. Anyway, so
we pick up now with the yud daled amud bet יד עמוד
ב yud daled amud bet at the third line before the lines
get wide. And now we turn from the physical scrolls as I
said to like the concepts of them as books of the Tanakh
תנ"ך. Tanakh. Tanu Rabbanan תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Sidran shel nevi'im סדרן
של נביאים, Sidran shel nevi'im, the order of the nevi'im נביאים. nevi'im.
Okay, what's just the order in which you have this? Now there's
an interesting question, well, you'll see, it's not going to look like
the order I bet that's in your little current Tanakh תנ"ך. Tanakh.
Now the question is what difference does it make? You know, I
mean, so you can think if you think of think of an
answer to that one. Okay,
let's take a look. Sidran shel nevi'im סדרן של נביאים, Sidran shel
nevi'im, Yehoshua ve-Shofetim יהושע ושופטים, Yehoshua ve-Shofetim, Shmuel u-Melakhim שמואל ומלכים Shmuel
u-Melakhim so so far that's chronological, Yirmiyah ve-Yekhezkel Yeshayahu ירמיה ויחזקאל ישעיהו.
Yirmiyah ve-Yekhezkel Yeshayahu. Oh, that's a little out of order. Okay, u-Shenei
Asar ושנים עשר. u-Shenei Asar. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara wants
to find out what that order's about. Nikhtei Hoshea kodem נכתיה הושע
קודם. Nikhtei Hoshea kodem. Now Hoshea הושע Hoshea comes first. Now dikhtiv
דכתיב dikhtiv tekhilat dibber Hashem be-Hoshea תחלת דבר ה' בהושע. tekhilat dibber
Hashem be-Hoshea. Ve-khi im Hoshea dibber tekhila וכי עם הושע דבר תחלה?
Ve-khi im Hoshea dibber tekhila? What do you mean the first thing
God did was spoke to Hoshea הושע? Hoshea? Ela mi-Moshe ve-ad Hoshea
kama nevi'im hayu אלא ממשה ועד הושע כמה נביאים היו? Ela mi-Moshe
ve-ad Hoshea kama nevi'im hayu? V'amar Rabbi Yochanan ואמר רבי יוחנן V'amar
Rabbi Yochanan Yeshayahu tekhila le-arba nevi'im she-nisnab'u be-oto haperek ישעיהו תחלה לארבעה
נביאים שנתנבאו באותו הפרק. Yeshayahu tekhila le-arba nevi'im she-nisnab'u be-oto haperek. So
it doesn't mean first from Yehoshua ve-Shofetim יהושע ושופטים Yehoshua ve-Shofetim etc.,
not first in the nevi'im rishonim נביאים ראשונים, nevi'im rishonim, but first
in the nevi'im acharonim נביאים אחרונים. nevi'im acharonim. Right, so you people
basically know nevi'im rishonim נביאים ראשונים nevi'im rishonim are the historical books
and nevi'im acharonim נביאים אחרונים nevi'im acharonim are the prophecies, are the
sort of
poetic prophecies. Obviously there's history in them as well. Okay, so of
the nevi'im acharonim נביאים אחרונים nevi'im acharonim Hoshea הושע Hoshea is the
first because there were actually four nevi'im נביאים nevi'im who roughly at
the same time and who are they? Nisnab'u be-oto haperek ve-elu hen
נתנבאו באותו הפרק ואלו הן: Nisnab'u be-oto haperek ve-elu hen: Hoshea ve-Yeshayahu,
Amos ve-Mikha הושע וישעיה עמוס ומיכה. Hoshea ve-Yeshayahu, Amos ve-Mikha. So therefore
and Hoshea הושע Hoshea was the first of them and Rashi רש"י
Rashi sort of gives you the exact chronology they didn't all exactly
overlap, but there was a lot of overlap. Ve-likdemei le-Hoshea be-reisha ולקדמיה
להושע ברישא. Ve-likdemei le-Hoshea be-reisha. So why not, so let's be chronological
and have Hoshea הושע Hoshea first. I mean, we would have had
Yeshayahu ישעיהו Yeshayahu first, like who here really knows Trei Asar תרי
עשר? Trei Asar? Okay, and to name all Trei Asar תרי עשר.
Trei Asar. There's a pop quiz. Anyway, I don't know. Anyway, but
let alone tell me what order they came in. Yoel, Chaggai, Zekharyah,
Malakhi יואל חגי זכריה מלאכי Yoel, Chaggai, Zekharyah, Malakhi are at the
end. That I know. Anyway, okay, so why don't we put Hoshea
הושע Hoshea first? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says be-reisha ברישא? be-reisha?
No, kivan de-khtiv nevu'atei gabbei Chaggai Zekharyah u-Malakhi כיון דכתיב נבואתיה גבי
חגי זכריה ומלאכי, kivan de-khtiv nevu'atei gabbei Chaggai Zekharyah u-Malakhi, there you
go, since it's part of Trei Asar תרי עשר Trei Asar and
Trei Asar תרי עשר Trei Asar is one book because each one
of those is too small to be its own book. So since
it's part of one book, ve-Chaggai Zekharyah u-Malakhi sof nevi'im havu וחגי
זכריה ומלאכי סוף נביאים הוו ve-Chaggai Zekharyah u-Malakhi sof nevi'im havu and
those were at the end, those were like beginning of Bayit Sheni
בית שני, Bayit Sheni, those were the very last nevi'im נביאים, nevi'im,
so khashiv lei bahadeihu חשיב ליה בהדייהו. khashiv lei bahadeihu. So therefore
it gets part of that group and that group was put at
the end. Okay, ve-likhtvei eilu le-chud ולכתביה איהו לחודיה ve-likhtvei eilu le-chud
or why put it part of that group? Have it as a
separate book. Ve-likdmei ולקדמיה Ve-likdmei and have it come first. I mean,
what do you mean? If it's not part of Trei Asar תרי
עשר, Trei Asar, have it as a separate book. Okay, ve-likdmei ולקדמיה
ve-likdmei put it first. Aidi de-zuta איידי דזוטא, Aidi de-zuta, no because
it's small, mirkas מירכס. mirkas. Now this is interesting. No, mirkas מירכס
mirkas means it will get lost. Now we are just thinking about
this as like conceptually. You know, you don't want to have a
tiny book of three chapters, right? But the Gemara גמרא Gemara is
thinking very practically. Right? If you have it as a separate book,
that means physically a separate book. You're going to write a little
scroll of Hoshea הושע. Hoshea. Okay, how many perakim פרקים perakim is
Hoshea הושע? Hoshea? Three? Fourteen. Fourteen. Oh, so it's not so small.
Okay, fine. So just shows it's been a while since I did
my Trei Asar תרי עשר. Trei Asar. Anyway, Yoel יואל Yoel is
three. Anyway, but still, fourteen, well, that's true. I mean, fourteen is
not so small. I mean, Megillat Esther מגילת אסתר Megillat Esther is
like ten. But I think that these are much smaller perakim פרקים
perakim than the Megilla מגילה. Megilla. I don't know. Anyway, all right.
All right,
we will talk about that, okay? I'm losing control. I see that.
Anyway, it's so small, so we're talking here about it as a
physical scroll. So a physical scroll that small will more easily get
lost and lose its identity. I mean, and we would say like
conceptually maybe, but this is sort of saying although you could say
no, if you put it as part of Trei Asar תרי עשר
Trei Asar they lose their identity because then you don't even know
their names. Okay, but anyway, but here we're talking not about conception.
We're talking about
physically. Because we're talking about a physical scroll, so they might want
to make this a separate ספר, Sefer, which would mean making it
a separate scroll. So therefore they put it as part of תרי
עשר. Trei Asar. Okay, and איכא. Ika. So מכדי, Michdee, so now
they're going to say fine, we got that, we got it as
part of תרי עשר. Trei Asar. So we got now, we're going
to go, it's not going to be first because תרי עשר Trei
Asar comes at the end. Okay, but let's still go chronologically. מכדי,
Michdee, let's take a look. ישעיהו קודם לירמיהו וליחזקאל. Yeshayahu kodem l'Yirmiyahu
u'l'Yechezkel. Yeah, clearly the chronology is ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, יחזקאל. Yechezkel.
Look and you look at any תנ"ך, Tanakh, that's the
chronology. לכתביה לישעיה ברישא. Lichtveia l'Yeshayahu b'reisha. Put ישעיהו Yeshayahu first. No,
כיון דמלכים סופיה חורבנא וירמיהו כוליה חורבנא. Kivan d'Melachim sofei churbana v'Yirmiyahu
kulei churbana. The מלכים Melachim end with the destruction of the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ירמיהו Yirmiyahu is all about prophesying the end of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, and you know, obviously ירמיהו Yirmiyahu
was sort of right there at the end of מלכים, Melachim, so
there's a clear continuity there. His is almost like the prophecy that
goes with the end of מלכים. Melachim. ויחזקאל רישא חורבנא וסיפיה נחמתא.
V'Yechezkel reisha churbana v'seifei nechamta. And it's true, there's like a very
nice thematic continuity. יחזקאל Yechezkel begins with the destruction of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? And then it like he's there in חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz and he hears about the destruction and all that,
but then there's like a נבואה nevuah of the third בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash etc. So therefore it's like a transition. חורבן, Churban, continuing
the חורבן, churban, a vision of the נבואה nevuah of the גאולה.
Geulah. וישעיהו כוליה נחמתא. V'Yeshayahu kulei nechamta. And ישעיהו Yeshayahu is all
about, you know, the vision of אחרית הימים. acharis hayamim. Not all,
of course. Anyway, different sections of ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. But anyway, סמכינן חורבנא
לחורבנא ונחמתא לנחמתא. Samchinan churbana l'churbana v'nechamta l'nechamta.
So we have this nice sort of thematic, because if you sort
of look at towards where they're pointing, okay, ישעיהו Yeshayahu historically came
earlier, but he's pointing towards אחרית הימים. acharis hayamim. Okay, so their
נבואה nevuah is, you know, נבואה nevuah of the חורבן, churban, נבואה
nevuah of the חורבן churban and then pointing to אחרית הימים, acharis
hayamim, then the final vision towards אחרית הימים. acharis hayamim. Now, okay,
that's not our order. You sort of understand that answer, but that's
not our order. So what do you think it matters, by the
way, in terms of this statement about what the order of the
נביאים Neviim are? Right? I mean, what was it, an instruction like,
but why what does it matter for us to say what the
order of the נביאים Neviim are? Exactly. The only reason it matters
to us, other than if I'm writing up a list and teaching
a class, is if you're going to print a book of תנ"ך,
Tanakh, what's the order I put it in? So for them too,
remember we taught earlier that you could put all of נביאים Neviim
in one scroll, right? That's what the גמרא Gemara taught earlier. Maybe
you can't put all תורה, נביאים וכתובים Torah, Neviim u'Ketuvim in one
scroll, but you could put all of נביאים Neviim in one scroll.
So if you're putting them all in one scroll, what's the order
you put them in? Okay, so obviously there's like a conceptual order,
but obviously it's not chronological. So is this also a pedagogical point,
if you wanted to be teaching it, this is the order you
should teach it? You know, is it thematic but not but not
pedagogical? But anyway, but it seems that the practical point is if
you're putting them all in one scroll, what's the order you put
them in? Then why don't we do it? That is a very
good question, because we don't put them all in one scroll.
So halakhically, like it's not mandated, you know. But we put it
all in one תנ"ך Tanakh like that? Yeah, I mean, that's not
the actual הלכה halakha here, the הלכה halakha is for a scroll.
But yeah, it's a good question like why we did not choose
to continue to follow that. Okay, but what we still don't understand
though, three of them, like whatever order they gave, yeah, like it
still seems that תרי עשר Trei Asar is out of order, right?
Okay, תרי עשר Trei Asar is going to be out of order.
תרי עשר Trei Asar is like a miscellaneous, it's a compilation. What
about the order those were written in? Oh, you mean within תרי
עשר, Trei Asar, what's the order? Oh, that's a good question. תרי
עשר Trei Asar itself is out of chronological order. Why do you
say that? Well because like didn't they just say הושע Hoshea is
first? I mean הושע, Hoshea, עמוס Amos and מיכה, Michah, right?
הושע Hoshea is first, then יואל, Yoel, חגי, Haggai, זכריה Zechariah and
מלאכי Malakhi is the end. Where is יואל? Yoel? I don't know.
Well how do you know that those are out of order? No,
but the גמרא Gemara just said over here. No, it also says
הושע Hoshea first and חגי, Haggai, זכריה Zechariah and מלאכי Malakhi at
the end. I saw that also in a פרק. perek. I mean
הושע, Hoshea, ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, עמוס Amos and מיכה. Michah. So here's הושע,
Hoshea, but then the יואל, Yoel, then you have עמוס, Amos, then
you have עובדיה Ovadyah and יונה. Yonah. Okay, I don't know, it's
a good question, it's a good question. Okay, the Christian Bible also
has different orders. Yeah, the Christian Bible also has different orders. What's
thematic and what's chronological? Yeah, the Christian Bible also has different divisions
and also has different division of פרקים prakim as well, you know.
So I mean, yeah, alright. So when Koren came out initially, I
don't know if they still do it, but when they came out
many years ago with their תנ"ך, Tanakh, they tried to institute a
new order of the פרקים prakim because of to make it more
Jewish in terms of the division. Of course nobody adopted it. Apparently
the reason, I don't know if this is true but it sounds
true, I heard this many years ago, that the reason we wound
up adopting the Christian division of the chapters was because they not
only divided it by chapter, but they came out with concordances. So
and maybe also in the disputations, we had to be able to
refer to the same, to the same thing. So we wound up
using, you know, their chapter divisions. So anyway, because we didn't have
chapter divisions, you know, we had סתומות ופתוחות stumot u'p'tuchot or whatever.
You give a nice order and you're able to be precise and
go exactly to where you're referring to. Anyway, but their order is
also different than our order. But it is a good question how
come our order shifted from what this is in this גמרא. Gemara.
סדרן של כתובים, Sidran shel Ketuvim, the order of the
כתובים: Ketuvim: רות וספר תהלים ואיוב. Rus v'sefer Tehillim v'Iyov. This has
nothing looks like our order of the תהלים... Tehillim... of the כתובים.
Ketuvim. I don't even know what our order of the כתובים Ketuvim
is because there's obviously not a clear chronological order. arc
like the נביאים. Nevi'im. Okay, רות Rus וספר תהלים ve-Sefer Tehillim ואיוב
ve-Iyov ומשלי u-Mishlei קהלת Kohelles שיר השירים Shir HaShirim וקינות, ve-Kinos, קינות
Kinos being איכה, Eicha, thank you. So you have קהלת, Kohelles, שיר
השירים, Shir HaShirim, and איכה, Eicha, those are the three of the
מגילות. Megillos. We put all the מגילות Megillos together.
דניאל ומגילת אסתר, Daniel u-Megillas Esther, עזרא ודברי הימים. Ezra ve-Divrei HaYamim.
Now this is much more chronological than our order. When it comes
to כתובים, Kesuvim, because it's such a miscellany, our order tends to
be a little more thematic. This order attempts to be more chronological.
One minute. ולמאן דאמר איוב בימי משה? U-le-man de-amar Iyov b'imei Moshe?
Okay, well that's what I was going to say. ולמאן דאמר איוב
בימי משה U-le-man de-amar Iyov b'imei Moshe now so that's now we're
assuming that so let's say so רות Rus comes first obviously, that's
the whatever great-great-grandmother of דוד, Dovid, then תהלים Tehillim which is דוד
המלך. Dovid HaMelech. איוב Iyov we're going to figure out when to
put איוב, Iyov, there's going to be a whole discussion of איוב.
Iyov. Okay, משלי Mishlei and קהלת Kohelles and שיר השירים Shir HaShirim
are all שלמה. Shlomo. Now we tend to like the idea that
שיר השירים Shir HaShirim was in his youth, it was about romance
and love, משלי Mishlei was about you know משלים, Mashalim, it was
חכמה, Chochmah, and קהלת Kohelles is a little more of a meditation
on death. So we tend to sort of think youth, middle age,
and death. Okay, here puts שיר השירים Shir HaShirim you know towards
the end. Okay, so we can discuss that a little bit, but
anyway what about Ezra and Nechemia too? What? Ezra... yeah, עזרא נחמיה
Ezra-Nechemia is a Christian division. According to חזל Chazal it's עזרא. Ezra.
עזרא נחמיה. Ezra-Nechemia. So we don't begin with suffering, I guess? Right.
Oh
what the... קהלת? Kohelles? Okay, anyway all right, quiet everybody, let me
finish. Okay, so anyway so that's שלמה. Shlomo. Why exactly that order
within שלמה Shlomo I'll discuss in a minute. Then קינות Kinos is
what do you call it, איכה, Eicha, thank you, that's חורבן הבית,
Churban HaBayis, so we jumped forward a few hundred years. דניאל Daniel
is during the during the period of גלות Galus between the two
בתי מקדש. Batei Mikdash. מגילת אסתר Megillas Esther according to classic חזל
Chazal chronology is towards the end of the גלות בבל, Galus Bavel,
and עזרא Ezra is the return, and דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim is
the is the end, you know obviously it goes starts way back
but it's written at the end. So this is a complete chronological
order with the one possible difference of the of the well איוב
Iyov we'll get to, but also the שיר השירים Shir HaShirim is
a little bit strange why that comes after משלי וקהלת. Mishlei ve-Kohelles.
And דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim is clearly not the last one chronologically,
well written, but certainly written at the end. Okay, so if you
take a look at תוספות, Tosafos,
תוספות Tosafos says well you know let's read a little גמרא Gemara
and then we'll talk about and then we'll discuss תוספות Tosafos then
we'll get because תוספות Tosafos is going on the later גמרא, Gemara,
what the order of the ספרים Sefarim of שלמה Shlomo was. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולמאן דאמר איוב בימי משה
היה U-le-man de-amar Iyov b'imei Moshe hayah so איוב Iyov was at
the time of משה Moshe because we're going to have a whole
discussion when was איוב. Iyov. So לכתביה לאיוב ברישא? Lichtivei le-Iyov be-reisha?
Why not put איוב Iyov first? אתחולי בפורענותא לא מתחלינן. Atchulei be-puranusa
lo matchilinan. We don't start with bad things. Obviously איוב Iyov was
all about the tragedy that befalls
him. Okay, רות נמי פורענותא היא? Rus nami puranusa hi? רות Rus
also starts with famine and leaving ישראל Yisrael and people dying. Na,
but פורענות דאית ליה אחרית. puranus de-is leih achris. No, but it
ends good, right? It ends by it has a very positive end
there, you know so I don't think איוב Iyov has a positive
end.
It's not גאולה, geulah, let's put it that way. It's not the
beginning of גאולה, geulah, okay, and
even the end of איוב Iyov leaves you very disturbed. Oh here
I'm going to make up for all your dead kids so I'm
going to give you more kids. What about the dead ones? Anyway,
but moving on, okay, but it doesn't matter, it's not the same
idea of גאולה, geulah, okay,
and it's also the basic story of רות Rus is an uplifting
one. רות Rus just starts with פורענות, puranus, the basic story is
not פורענות. puranus. The whole story of איוב Iyov is פורענות. puranus.
אמר רבי יוחנן למה נקרא שמה רות שיצא ממנה דוד שריוהו להקדוש
ברוך הוא Amar Rabbi Yochanan lama nikra shemah Rus she-yatzah mimenu Dovid
she-rivahu le-Hakadosh Baruch Hu so רות ריוהו, Rus rivahu, sated God, בשירות
ותשבחות. be-shiros ve-sishbachos. Okay, which also explains why רות Rus then leads
into תהלים. Tehillim. All right, but there's a clear you know רות
Rus is basically a positive story. Okay, now before we get to
מי כתבן, Mi Kasvan, let's just look at תוספות. Tosafos. בפורענותא לא
מתחלינן Be-puranusa lo matchilinan about איוב. Iyov. So תוספות Tosafos says: ואם
תאמר ונכתביה מיד אחר רות? Ve-im tomar ve-nichtivei miyad achar Rus? Okay,
so if איוב Iyov still was early, then as soon as we
start with something good, רות, Rus, let's throw in איוב. Iyov. So
the obvious point is no, רות Rus leads into תהלים Tehillim and
so on and so forth, which leads into שלמה, Shlomo, which leads
into דוד Dovid and דוד Dovid leads into שלמה. Shlomo. ואמרי משום
דאחרית דרוס היה אחרית שיצא ממנו דוד שריוהו להקדוש ברוך הוא בשירות
ותשבחות. Ve-amri mishum she-achris she-Rus hayah achris she-yatzah mimenu Dovid she-rivahu le-Hakadosh
Baruch Hu be-shiros ve-sishbachos. That's the obvious point, רות Rus flows into
תהלים Tehillim because into דוד המלך. Dovid HaMelech. ולכך כתבו אחר כך
מיד אותן שירות ואחרית
שלה. Ve-lachach kasavo achar kach miyad osan shiros ve-achris she-lah. ואם תאמר
למאן
דאמר מעולי גולה היה Ve-im tomar le-man de-amar mi-olei golah hayah
now according to those that say that איוב, Iyov, we're going to
have an opinion later that says that איוב Iyov was amongst those
that returned in the בית שני Bayis Sheini period. לכתביה לאיוב לבסוף?
Lichtivei le-Iyov le-vasof?
So write איוב Iyov at the very end, write it together with
עזרא. Ezra. ואמרי דמשום הכי כתבו בהדי תהלים ומשלי. Ve-amri de-mishum hachi
kasavo bahadei Tehillim u-Mishlei.
Here's why we sort of said איוב תהלים... Iyov Tehillim... תהלים Tehillim,
*Tehillim* איוב Iyov *Iyov* משלי Mishlei, *Mishlei* קהלת Kohelet, *Koheles* שיר השירים
Shir ha-Shirim *Shir Hashirim*, right? What, איוב Iyov, *Iyov* is stuck in
the middle? תהלים Tehillim, *Tehillim* should be followed with משלי Mishlei, *Mishlei*
קהלת Kohelet *Koheles* and שיר השירים Shir ha-Shirim *Shir Hashirim*. Right? So
why did איוב Iyov *Iyov* come right after תהלים Tehillim, *Tehillim* and
broke up the ספרים *Sefarim* of דוד David *David* and of שלמה
Shlomo *Shlomo*? So if you say איוב Iyov, *Iyov* was early, so
fine, we wanted to get through רות Rut, *Rus* and תהלים Tehillim.
*Tehillim* which go together essentially, that's because that's דוד המלך *David Hamelech*,
and we did it right after. But if איוב Iyov *Iyov* was
late, what is he doing in between that list? So he says
משום הכי כתבו katvu, בהדי תהלים Tehillim ומשלי *Mishum hakhi katvo behadei
Tehillim u-Mishlei* לפי שהוא מענין אחד *Lefi she-hu me-inyan echad* כתובים Kesuvim
מעין שירה *Ketuvim me-ein shira*. Now what does it mean they're one
ענין *Inyan*? איוב Iyov. *Iyov* משלי Mishlei *Mishlei* קהלת Kohelet, *Koheles* are
the same idea? They're completely different ideas. No. כתובים Kesuvim מעין שירה
*Ketuvim me-ein shira* ומקראות קצרים *U-mikraos ketzarim* וניגון אחד *Ve-niggun echad*. So
there is a, it's not only the same genre, the actual, if
you ever looked at the טראפ *Trop* on those ספרים *Sefarim*, okay,
which is, you know, which is what do you call it, which
is איוב Iyov *Iyov* תהלים Tehillim. *Tehillim* and משלי Mishlei, *Mishlei*, the
טראפ *Trop* does not, it looks crazy. It's not the normal טראפ
*Trop*. Meaning it's the normal thing, same symbols, but you can't read
them the normal way. So there's a special טראפ *Trop* for those
three ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh. *Sifrei Kodesh*. Okay? I don't know it,
but whatever. Yeah, I'm sure they did.
People know it nowadays too. I think. I don't know it. Anyway,
there's a special טראפ *Trop*. And that's the reason there's a special
טראפ *Trop* is because those are all poetry, but also poetry of
like, you know, there's a lot of the תורה'ס *Torah's* poetry. You
could say ישעיהו Yeshayahu *Yeshayahu* is poetry. But it's poetry of a
certain type of like, you know, sides of the verse and therefore
calls for a different type of a טראפ *Trop* and they're all
written in the same style. So it's not just they're all poetry
because there's a lot of the ספרי כתובים *Sifrei Kesuvim* that's poetry,
but it's poetry in the same style and the style that demands
a specific type of a טראפ *Trop*. And therefore they go together.
What? You say one sentence, what do you mean that they're like
crazy or crazy? No, the טראפ *Trop*, it doesn't make sense. Meaning
like if you're used to מרכא טפחא מונח אתנחתא *Mercha tipcha munach
esnachto*, you're gonna like, you don't get that. You get stuff, if
you take a look at it, it's like "what?", like the symbols
don't match the normal way symbols appear, you know, in normal ספרי
תנך sifrei Tanach, *Sifrei Tanakh*. Okay, you'll look at it later. Okay.
משום הכי כתבו בהדי תהלים Tehillim ומשלי *Mishum hakhi katvo behadei Tehillim
u-Mishlei* לפי שהוא מענין אחד *Lefi she-hu me-inyan echad* כתובים מעין שירה
*Ketuvim me-ein shira*, so it's a poetry, ומקראות קצרים *U-mikraos ketzarim*, very
short verses, וניגון אחד *Ve-niggun echad*. דמהימם הוה ניגון *D'mahimam hava niggun*
כדאמרינן דקרא בספר דברי אלהים מפורש בשום שכל *Ke-de-amrinan dikra be-sefer divrei
Elokim meforash beshum sechel*. מאי בשום שכל *Mai beshum sechel*? פסוקי טעמיה
*Pesukei ta'amei*. So actually going all the way back, they had a
distinctive way of being read. It was poetry which had a particular
meter and a particular way of being read, different not only than
the other prose of תנך Tanach *Tanakh*, but even than the other
poetry of תנך Tanach, *Tanakh*. And that actually is true in terms
of the symbols that we still have about them. Okay, so now
we've got that
איוב Iyov, *Iyov* משלי Mishlei, *Mishlei* קהלת Kohelet *Koheles* go together. Okay?
So now the question is why that order? Why that order? ולהדיא
לא כתבו אחר משלי *Ve-hadaya lo katvo achar Mishlei*? So why didn't
I write משלי *Mishlei* קהלת *Koheles* and איוב Iyov *Iyov* if איוב
Iyov. *Iyov* was actually later? משום שלא להפסיק דברי שלמה Shlomo *Mishum
she-lo le-hafsik divrei Shlomo* because we wanted the books of שלמה Shlomo
*Shlomo* to be together. So משלי *Mishlei* קהלת *Koheles* and שיר השירים
Shir ha-Shirim *Shir Hashirim*, this explains everything. This is a brilliant תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafos*. משלי *Mishlei* קהלת *Koheles* and שיר השירים Shir ha-Shirim *Shir
Hashirim* are the three books of שלמה Shlomo. *Shlomo*. Okay. איוב Iyov
*Iyov*, right?
You have, I left this undone. Okay. We have
משלי *Mishlei* קהלת *Koheles* and שיר השירים *Shir Hashirim* are the three
books of שלמה Shlomo. *Shlomo*. איוב Iyov, *Iyov* goes together with these
two. Okay? So here you have תהלים Tehillim *Tehillim* mentioned. Okay? So
where are you gonna put איוב Iyov *Iyov*? Okay? You can't put
it chronologically after because you want to group it with these two.
שיר השירים *Shir Hashirim* is not part of the group, right? So
the only, and you want to keep these three together. So the
only place you can put איוב Iyov *Iyov* to create this group
of the three that have the same type of טראפ *Trop* is
to put איוב Iyov *Iyov* here. That allows you to group the
similar טראפים *Trops* together and to group the books of שלמה Shlomo.
*Shlomo* together. So that's why we have this order and that's why
also שיר השירים *Shir Hashirim*, which we could argue is chronologically earlier,
did not appear here because, actually no, you couldn't say that, because
why didn't you do שיר השירים משלי קהלת Mishlei Kohelet, איוב Iyov
*Shir Hashirim Mishlei Koheles Iyov*? Ah, you could have done that. So
that doesn't fully explain it. But anyway, but this explains at least
this order. And why not have איוב Iyov *Iyov* as early as
possible? Oh, I guess if איוב Iyov, *Iyov* was early, you wanted
to get it as early as possible. Right, but assuming when he's
from, assuming when he's from, but that's debatable. Wait, let me just
finish reading. Okay. ורבינו תם מפרש שלכך כתבו בהדי תהלים Tehillim, משום
דאמר לקמן דוד כתב ספרו וכולי *Ve-Rabbeinu Tam mefaresh she-likach katvo behadei
Tehillim mishum d'amar le-kaman David katav sipro ve-khu*. Okay, I don't want
to get into that. Okay, yes. I'm curious to know whether the
reason poetry came first is because poetry is metaphorical. Yeah. So it
should be, it should be examined in a bit of a different
light, wouldn't you say? Totally, but these aren't the only books of
poetry. They're a particular type of poetry. But yes, that's correct, right?
But you had רות Rut *Rus* which wasn't poetry, so it's not
all the poetic
books. Okay,
now we get to that's the order, okay, now we get to
who the authors are. ומי כתבן, who wrote them, who authored them?
It doesn't mean who took pen to paper necessarily, okay, but it
is an interesting question about who wrote them because well, we'll see
that in a minute. But anyway, who are the authors? משה כתב
ספרו ופרשת בלעם. Moshe katav sifro uparshat Bilam.
Very interesting that it identifies בלעם Bilam separately. You would say the
whole thing is תורת משה. Torat Moshe. He didn't say משה כתב
ספרו ספר בראשית, Moshe katav sifro sefer Bereishit, right? בראשית Bereishit occurred
before משה. Moshe. פרשת שמות, Parshat Shemot, פרשת שמות Parshat Shemot occurred
before משה, Moshe, I mean the first two פסוקים pesukim at least
before he was born. But yes, the point is that פרשת בלעם
Parshat Bilam is told totally from the frame of reference of an
outsider frame of reference, not a משה Moshe frame of reference. It's
looked at from the outsiders, right? There's no בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
are looked at there as the other, it's not בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael looking towards others, right? You have the נבואה nevuah of בלעם,
Bilam, so you could sort of imagine, right? You don't sort of
have the omniscient narrator that's looking at everything from the perspective of
בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, right? You don't have that there. So you
could sort of conceptualize that as almost like a different type of
a perspective. Anyway, nevertheless, that obviously is part of the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah and that's part of משה. Moshe. Okay, so
where were
we? ואיוב, VeIyov, and ספר איוב, Sefer Iyov, assuming איוב Iyov was
בימי משה. biyemei Moshe. Also because איוב, Iyov of course, deals with
the basic question about, you know, צדיק ורע לו רשע וטוב לו,
tzadik vera lo rasha vetov lo, and you know, משה Moshe says
הודעני נא את דרכיך, hodeini na et derachecha, which חז"ל Chazal understand
means that משה Moshe wants to understand why is it that the
wicked prosper, right? That's not in the פסוקים, pesukim, but that's how
חז"ל Chazal understand. משה חכם מכל אדם, Moshe chacham mikol adam, so
therefore you, well that's שלמה חכם מכל אדם. Shlomo chacham mikol adam.
But משה Moshe stopped at the 50th level, you know, of whatever.
So anyway, so it makes sense to assign איוב Iyov to משה.
Moshe. יהושע כתב ספרו ושמונה פסוקים שבתורה, Yehoshua katav sifro ushmonah pesukim
shebaTorah, the last eight פסוקים pesukim which is after משה Moshe died.
Okay, so
שמואל כתב ספרו ושופטים. Shmuel katav sifro veShoftim. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel
wrote his book and שופטים Shoftim because obviously שופטים Shoftim is all
the שופטים, Shoftim, so the person who wrote שופטים Shoftim had to
come after the שופטים, Shoftim, okay? And שמואל Shmuel is a נביא,
navi, so that's שמואל Shmuel wrote his
ספר. sefer. ורות, veRut, and the book of רות, right? Because the
book of רות is ויהי בימי שפוט השופטים. vayehi biyemei shefot hashoftim.
שמואל Shmuel dies halfway through the book of שמואל? Shmuel? Yeah. Yeah.
That's an interesting question, so who wrote the end of שמואל Shmuel
according to this?
שמואל? Shmuel? He could have been, but if משה Moshe didn't write
the last eight פסוקים pesukim of the תורה, Torah, then who wrote
the, then why, okay, that's interesting. דוד כתב ספר תהלים על ידי
עשרה זקנים, David katav sefer Tehillim al yedei asarah zekenim, so he
did it as a collaborative effort here with, you know, ten other
authors. Well, at least they didn't sort of collaborate on the same
תהלים, but they authored their individual פרקים. perakim. על ידי אדם הראשון
על ידי מלכי צדק על ידי אברהם על ידי משה ועל ידי
הימן ועל ידי ידותון. Al yedei Adam Harishon, al yedei Malki-Tzedek, al
yedei Avraham, al yedei Moshe, ve'al yedei Heman, ve'al yedei Yedutun. These
are names actually of particular פרקי תהלים, pirkei Tehillim, you know, it
mentions that this is for this person or whatever by this person.
משכיל להימן, Maskil leHeman, למנצח לידותון, Lamnatzeiach liYedutun, ועל ידי אסף ועל
ידי שלושה בני קרח. ve'al yedei Asaf ve'al yedei shloshah bnei Korach.
Okay, so you know, there's a מזמור לבני קרח. mizmor livnei Korach.
Right, מזמור שיר לבני קרח. mizmor shir livnei Korach. Okay, ירמיה, Yirmeyah,
I don't know the answer
to
the
book of
שמואל, Shmuel, how he's supposed to have written his own book. How
about מלכי צדק? Malki-Tzedek? We will get to it. Okay, ירמיה כתב
ספרו וספר מלכים. Yirmeyah katav sifro veSefer Melachim. ירמיה Yirmeyah wrote his
book and the book of מלכים, Melachim, which is of course goes
up to the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, all through
the destruction, וקינות, vekinot, and איכה, Eichah, which is all about the
destruction of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Okay, חזקיה
וסיעתו, Chizkiyah vesiato, חזקיה Chizkiyah and his group, כתבו, wrote
ישעיה משלי שיר השירים וקהלת. Yeshayah Mishlei Shir Hashirim veKohelet. Now that's
very interesting why it assigns all of those. Okay, so if you
look at רש"י, Rashi,
why ישעיה? Yeshayah? Why not say ישעיהו Yeshayahu wrote his own ספר?
sefer? So look at רש"י: Rashi: כתב ישעיה שהרגו מנשה ולא כתב
ספרו. katav Yeshayah sheharago Menashe velo katav sifro. ישעיה Yeshayah didn't get
a chance to write his own ספר, sefer, שלא היו נביאים כותבין
ספריהן אלא לפני מותן. shelo hayu neviim kotvin sifreihen ela lifnei motan.
They only wrote it towards the end of their life when they
were done with all their prophesying, and if ישעיה Yeshayah died a
violent death, he didn't, you know, he didn't anticipate his own death
and therefore he didn't have a chance to write his own ספר.
sefer. Now, why are we assigning it to חזקיה? Chizkiyah? Because if
you take a look at the, because it says actually in קהלת,
if you look at the next
רש"י, Rashi, משלי קהלת, רש"י Rashi says. דכתב בספר משלי אשר העתיקו
אנשי חזקיה. de-khasav be-seifer Mishlei asher he-etiku anshei Chizkiyah. It actually says
in משלי, these are the משלי שלמה Mishlei Shlomo which were copied
down by the people of חזקיה. Chizkiyah. וחזקיה גרם להם לעסוק בתורה
כדאמרינן בחלק נעץ חרב על פתח בית המדרש ניקבו הדבר שמו. ve-Chizkiyah
garam la-hem la-asok ba-Torah ke-de-amrinan be-Cheilek na'atz cherev al pesach beis ha-medrash
nikbu ha-davar shemo.
So it actually did not was not limited to his time because
ישעיהו Yeshayahu, actually continued after חזקיהו Chizkiyahu died, right? So the book
of ישעיהו, Yeshayahu so it wasn't by חזקיה, Chizkiyah, but it was
by חזקיה Chizkiyah and his enterprise. Okay, the people he had, he
had a group of people that their job was to write ספרי
קודש. So basically he wrote משלי שיר השירים וקהלת Mishlei Shir ha-Shirim
ve-Kohelet and then when after ישעיהו Yeshayahu had died, they wrote the
ספר ישעיהו. sefer Yeshayahu. It is very interesting, right, why redacted, yeah,
I mean not that they authored, right, the idea being that שלמה
Shlomo was the one who actually said משלי, but they were the
ones that like right, I mean that's an important question, right? What
does it mean to author, to write? It means that they took
all of the משלים, meshalim, like what do we imagine, right? When
it says אשר העתיקו אנשי חזקיה, asher he-etiku anshei Chizkiyah, what I
probably imagine, it's good that you stopped me there, probably imagine is,
you know that שלמה Shlomo's didn't say it as a book. שלמה
Shlomo. didn't say, "Okay, Chapter 1. Okay, Chapter 2." Right? Over his
life, right, he said... right, which many uses his word processor, he
said different משלים. meshalim. People either remembered them or copied them down,
whatever, you had all these different משלים meshalim that were said. And
then they, you know, organized, redacted, whatever, it's interesting to ask like
what exactly did they do? תהלים, right? So, although they didn't do
תהלים, but you know, now שיר השירים is more interesting because שיר
השירים does seem to actually be a coherent, clearly like a coherent,
what? No, separate poems. Really? Yes, separate poems. Yes, lots of them.
Really? Okay.
Maybe it was my attempt always to read it as some type
of a continuous narrative. Attempt to read it as one long, right,
allegory, right.
קהלת clearly are sort of separate units, right? So all of these
and if you think about it, a book like ישעיהו Yeshayahu. as
opposed to a book like ירמיהו, Yirmeyahu, ירמיהו Yirmeyahu also, it's not
all chronological, but there's much more of a chronological arc to ירמיהו
Yirmeyahu than there is to ישעיהו. Yeshayahu So all of these things
could have existed as like units, you know, separate like pieces, had
to be like organized and redacted and edited and so on. So
since actually in משלי it assigns that task to חזקיה Chizkiyah for
משלי, it's going to assign it for like all of these works.
I do think it is interesting that it doesn't want to sort
of what set why felt compelled to extend that to שיר השירים
and קהלת, right? There was enough no reason it couldn't have said
that שיר השירים and קהלת were straight by שלמה. But maybe once
they were sort of saying it by משלי, they decided that they
were going to say that they would logically extend it to those
two as well. Yes, Bobby. This sounds a bit weird, but were
there any editors involved with you know, when somebody is doing all
this for someone else? Right, it seems that that's very specific... yeah,
I mean we have no idea, but it does say אשר העתיקו
אנשי חזקיה. asher he-etiku anshei Chizkiyah. It has a group that's actually
working on them. I mean that's the most amazing thing, that this
is the one ספר sefer in תנ"ך that actually reflects on the
process on like who wrote it, that itself testifies to who sort
of like you know, sort of compiled it at least. Okay, I
mean העתיקו he-etiku is like compiled, who compiled it? All right? All
right,
so that was really interesting, particularly the ישעיהו Yeshayahu one, but all
of these, ישעיהו and all the books of שלמה. Okay. אנשי כנסת
הגדולה כתבו, Anshei Knesset ha-Gedolah kasvu, now the people of כנסת הגדולה,
Knesset ha-Gedolah, which was
the beginning of the second בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, חגי זכריה ומלאכי,
Chaggai Zecharya u-Malachi, כתבו יחזקאל, kasvu Yechezkel, which was why didn't יחזקאל
Yechezkel write? Right, yeah, why do we assume יחזקאל Yechezkel himself didn't
write it? רש"י Rashi says, oh, right, רש"י Rashi says, oh well
let me first read the
end. יחזקאל ושנים עשר. Yechezkel ve-Shneim Asar. Okay, דניאל ומגילת אסתר Daniel
u-Megillas Esther ומגילת אסתר. u-Megillas Esther. Now those are all, so those
are all the books of that existed in גלות. galus. I mean
יחזקאל Yechezkel was in גלות, galus, ושנים עשר ve-Shneim Asar was a
whole was a whole collection, but it ended with the אנשי כנסת
הגדולה, Anshei Knesset ha-Gedolah, so it assigns that to them, חגי זכריה
ומלאכי, Chaggai Zecharya u-Malachi, and דניאל ומגילת אסתר Daniel u-Megillas Esther were
in גלות. galus. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says, כתבו יחזקאל שנתנבא בבבל ואיני יודע למה לא כתבו יחזקאל בעצמו
אם לא מפני שלא ניתנה נבואה לכתוב בחוץ לארץ וכתבום אלו אחר
שבאו לארץ. kasvu Yechezkel she-nisnabe ve-Vavel ve-eini yodeia lama lo kesavo Yechezkel
be-atzmo im lo mipenei she-lo nisna nevuah le-hikasev be-chutz la-aretz ve-kasvum elu
achar she-bau la-aretz.
Maybe you don't write down the ספרי תנ"ך, you're not initially the
author. Maybe the prophecy was given in חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, but
they actually do not become a book of תנ"ך, you know, in
its final form to be part of the canon, that process of
sort of only happens in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay. That's problematic
for אסתר. Esther. וכן ספר דניאל שהיה בגלות וכן מגילת אסתר. ve-chein
seifer Daniel she-hayah ba-galus ve-chein Megillas Esther. No, because we're assigning all
of that to אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset ha-Gedolah. So רש"י Rashi
says we want to assign them the task of taking these books
of נבואה nevuah that existed in the גלות, galus, or these books
of not נבואה, nevuah, whatever of רוח הקודש, ruach ha-kodesh, of divine
inspiration that existed in the גלות galus and of making them part
of the canon and making them in their final edited form and
we want to assign and that enterprise having taken place in ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. Yes, that's the end of אסתר *Esther*? That אסתר
*Esther* wrote. Yeah, but then the, so that's a good point, but
then the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* in מגילה *Megilla* has a famous thing
where אסתר *Esther* writes to אנשי כנסת הגדולה *Anshei Knesses HaGedolah*, כתבוני
לדורות *kitvuni l'dorot*. You ever hear that phrase? Famous מדרש Midrash *Midrash*
from אסתר *Esther*, which basically means, okay, I wrote it down as
a, as a book. I want you to include me in the
canon. That actually is exactly that bridge, right? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
in מגילת אסתר *Megillat Esther* says, אמרה אסתר *amra Esther* to אנשי
כנסת הגדולה *Anshei Knesses HaGedolah*, I think, כתבוני *kitvuni*, כתבוני לדורות *kitvuni
l'dorot*. So לדורות *l'dorot* means put me in the canon. So they,
so again, maybe they didn't do any editing, maybe all they did
was they decided to make it as part of the canon, right?
Which does raise that interesting question, right? That is this a process
of like editing it as a book or is this a process
also of just like saying, no, no, no, the whole thing sort
of was there, we like we assigned it as part of the
canon. The basic assumption is that it was the אנשי *Anshei*, even
if you sort of these books existed prior, the ultimate sort of
decisions of what's in the canon, right? I mean, so a lot
we assume was like the אנשי כנסת הגדולה *Anshei Knesses HaGedolah*, but
to some degree, it was left to the time of the תנאים
*Tannaim*. Because there were debate, the Halachic law of מטמא את הידיים
*metamei es hayadayim* is ספרי קודש *sifrei kodesh* is מטמא את הידיים
*metamei es hayadayim*. The books of תנ"ך *Tanach* cause your hands to
become טמא *tamei*, that's a, so they shouldn't store the תנ"ך *Tanach*
with the תרומה *Terumah* ודלמא אתי למיכל *v'dilma ati l'meichal*. I also
think it's just a way that you give it like power, if
you know, if it has this impact that it makes your hands
טמא *tamei*. So anyway, though the Halachic discussions around which of the
ספרי תנ"ך *sifrei Tanach*, which things are מטמא את הידיים *metamei es
hayadayim* is really the discussion of which books are part of the
canon. And there are debates about things like, you know, שיר השירים
*Shir HaShirim* and יחזקאל *Yechezkel* and all those things which you could
imagine there were debates whether to include in the canon or not,
there were debates about whether they were מטמא את הידיים *metamei es
hayadayim*. So to some degree, this is not yet the full discussion
of who finalized the canon, that was actually at the Tannaic period
of מטמא את הידיים *metamei es hayadayim*, but that was maybe the
final debates about the things which maybe had been some question about.
Okay, probably even before that, like nobody ever questioned that ישעיהו *Yeshayahu*
and ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu* or whatever were part of the canon, right? So
one does wonder to what degree part of this enterprise was the
editing and the finalizing in book form, and to what degree this
enterprise was assigning it as part of the canon. I think מגילת
אסתר *Megillat Esther* is a great example because according to the own
testimony of מגילת אסתר *Megillat Esther*, she wrote it, but according to,
you know, this sort of מדרש Midrash *Midrash* and this thing אנשי
כנסת הגדולה *Anshei Knesses HaGedolah*, they had to decide we're taking this
and making it part of the canon. Yes. We're distinguishing three stages:
authorship, writing it down, and then final canonization. Right. So when it
says כתבו *katvu* right now, it's not clear from... well, right, right.
I mean, I don't know if כתבו *katvu* also is necessarily the
physical writing down, meaning you can imagine an, it is the physical
writing down, but it's the editing process, right? ישעיהו
*Yeshayahu* clearly said all of his prophecies. But who organized them this
way, edited them this way, put it in final book form? Right,
so the כתבו *katvu* here is the question about like editing and
organizing and creating it in its redact, in its final form. Okay,
but I think the אסתר *Esther* point is a good one. Okay,
עזרא כתב ספרו *Ezra katav sipro*, עזרא *Ezra* wrote his ספר *sefer*,
והיחס של דברי הימים עד לו *v'hayachas shel Divrei HaYamim ad lo*,
and the entire chronology of דברי הימים *Divrei HaYamim* until it got
to him. Okay, now I don't know who wrote the chronology of
דברי הימים *Divrei HaYamim* after that. מסייע ליה לרב *msayei lei l'Rav*,
this supports רב Rav *Rav*. דאמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב *d'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, לא עלה עזרא מבבל עד שיחס עצמו ועלה
*lo ala Ezra miBavel ad sheyiches atzmo v'ala*, until he sort of,
you know, got all the way figured out his genealogy, because a
lot of the whole enterprise there at the beginning of the return
was to determine, you know, who people's genealogies, like to get the
נביאים nevi'im, *Neviim* and the כהנים *Kohanim* back in order, to figure
out about all the foreign wives. So that's why a lot of
דברי הימים *Divrei HaYamim* is also that whole genealogy thing. Okay.
Right, exactly. Okay. Now, ומאן אסקיא *u'man askeih*? So who finished ספר
עזרא *sefer Ezra*? נחמיה בן חכליה אסקיא *Nechemiah ben Chakalyah askeih*, so
נחמיה *Nechemiah* finished ספר עזרא *sefer Ezra*. Okay, phew. That was the
whole thing. Now, אמר מר *amar mar*, now we're going to go
unpack it. All right, so יהושע כתב ספרו Yehoshua katav sifro. ושמונה
פסוקים pesukim, שבתורה *Yehoshua katav sipro u'shmonah pesukim shebaTorah*, he wrote the
last eight פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*. תניא כמאן דאמר *tanya k'man d'amar*, שמונה
פסוקים shemonah pesukim שבתורה יהושע Yehoshua, כתבן *shmonah pesukim shebaTorah Yehoshua katavan*,
יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua* wrote the last eight פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*. דתניא *d'tanya*,
וימת שם משה Moshe. עבד ה' *vayamas sham Moshe eved Hashem*, right?
That's, the last eight פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* starts with that. משה Moshe
*Moshe* died. אפשר *efshar* משה Moshe? *Moshe* מת *mes* was dead or
whatever, you know, אפשר וכתב וימת שם משה Moshe *efshar v'katav Vayamas
sham Moshe* or אפשר משה Moshe כתב וימת שם משה Moshe *efshar
Moshe katav Vayamas sham Moshe*? That it was possible that משה Moshe
*Moshe* was writing משה Moshe, *Moshe* died? אלא Ella, עד כאן כתב
משה, Moshe מכאן ואילך Mikan ve-eilach, כתב יהושע Yehoshua *ela ad kan
katav Moshe, mikan v'eilach katav Yehoshua*, דברי רבי Rebbe יהודה *divrei Rabbi
Yehuda*. Right? Fine, he didn't write the last eight פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*,
that was written by יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua*. It's not just a question
of who put pen to paper. It means that the divine prophecy
to have that as part of the תורה, Torah that was given
to יהושע, Yehoshua. that was not given to משה. Moshe So that
could be seen as very heretical. ואמר ליה רב כהנא אמר ליה
רבי שמעון אפשר ספר תורה חסר אות אחת? Ve-amar lei Rav Kahana
amar lei Rabi Shimon efshar sefer Torah chasar os achas? What? Is
it possible that the ספר תורה—could sefer Torah read it
physically, the ספר תורה sefer Torah משה Moshe, wrote was not a
finished book? But obviously it also is more religiously: is it possible
that what we consider the ספר תורה sefer Torah was not all
through the prophecy of משה? Moshe דכתיב לקוח את ספר התורה הזה.
Dechasiv Lakoach es sefer haTorah hazeh.
Now again, he's reading it very physically in terms of the book.
משה Moshe takes the ספר תורה sefer Torah and gives it to
the כהנים לויים. kohanim leviyim. So clearly it was complete in משה's
Moshe time. אלא עד כאן הקדוש ברוך הוא אומר ומשה אומר וכותב.
Ela ad kan Hakadosh Baruch Hu omer u-Moshe omer ve-chosev.
Until this point, God is dictating and משה Moshe, is repeating and
writing, if that's our גרסא. girsa. מכאן ואילך, those last eight פסוקים,
pesukim. הקדוש ברוך הוא אומר ומשה כותב בדמע. Hakadosh Baruch Hu omer
u-Moshe kosev bedema.
From that point on, God is saying and משה Moshe writes it
as he's crying. Okay? So God is still dictating and it had
to all be written by משה, Moshe it had to all be
משה's Moshe prophecy. So משה Moshe was writing it, was crying as
he was writing. כמי שנאמר להלן ויאמר להם ברוך מפיו יקרא אלי
את כל הדברים האלה ואני כותב על הספר בדיו. Kemi shenemar le-hallan
vayomer lahem Baruch mipiv yikra eilay es kol hadevarim ha-eileh va-ani kosev
al hasefer bedyo.
And I was writing in the book with ink. So משה, Moshe
therefore, like direct dictation, the whole thing was direct dictation, even though
משה Moshe was crying as he wrote. Now, I should say two,
well one is a sort of just a brilliant חאפ chap of
the הגר"א, Gra, but the other is the important thing about this
besides its question of who wrote the last eight פסוקים pesukim and
can we allow for the fact that those last eight פסוקים pesukim.
were not directly משה's Moshe. prophecy, is also the idea of the
model of what it means
that the תורה מסיני Torah mi-Sinai model, the sense of the
תורה Torah is from God, that the idea that תורה מן השמים
Torah min hashamayim means every single word was directly dictated. God said,
okay, sit down and take dictation, write the following
word, word-for-word dictated, is primarily this גמרא, Gemara right? Other גמרות Gemoros
talk about the concept of תורה מסיני Torah mi-Sinai and so on
and don't
exactly—now they do say anybody who thinks that even one פסוק pasuk
משה מפי עצמו, Moshe mipi atzmo, that person אין לו חלק לעולם
הבא. ein lo cheilek l'olam haba. But there's a gap between writing
מפי עצמו mipi atzmo and taking direct
dictation, right? There's all space in between about
being a נבואה, nevuah, being divinely inspired, but it's not word-for-word dictation.
So the model of word-for-word dictation is primarily this גמרא Gemara and
that is of course the very
standard model
of what
תורה מסיני Torah mi-Sinai means. So it's become the standard model. The
question is, is it the only model in
the גמרא Gemara is a different question. So that's really important. What?
It's the only model even here. Well, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
doesn't even... Well, for the last eight פסוקים. psukim, But the last
eight פסוקים aside, it certainly is—but it was only introduced by the
second תנא. Tanna. That's true. You make a good point. Even this
model of direct dictation wasn't mentioned by the first תנא, Tanna, it
was only mentioned by the second. They're debating the last eight פסוקים.
So this is really important in terms of that sense of what
does it mean,
תורה מן השמים Torah min hashamayim and direct dictation? That model is
from here. It's not echoed in other places or it's not stated
in other places. The other interesting thing is the הגר"א Gra makes
a point because the הגר"א Gra is still bothered by this idea
that משה Moshe, is writing about his own death before it happened.
So he actually makes an interesting point that the
פסוק pasuk it quotes by Jeremiah dictating and ברוך Baruch writing down,
אני כותב על הספר בדיו, ani kosev al hasefer bedyo, I would
write on the book with ink. So the הגר"א Gra says if
you look at the earlier statement about משה, Moshe's it says משה
כותב בדמע. Moshe kosev bedema. So the word אני כותב על הספר
בדיו ani kosev al hasefer bedyo is paralleled with משה כותב בדמע
Moshe kosev bedema with tears. So what the הגר"א Gra actually says,
the word דמע dema does not just mean a tear, it means
like דמוע dimua which means like mixed up. He sort of says
that
משה Moshe? wrote the letters but they were sort of some type
of a word jumble or something like that, so it didn't... and
then יהושע came and he organized it. I don't even exactly remember,
but in some mystical
way משה Moshe. wrote it like in invisible ink with tears or
something like that. But so you have both. You have משה Moshe,
actually having authored it but it not yet being crystallized or the
words forming until יהושע sort of finalized it after משה Moshe died.
A way to sort of strike the balance there. Yes. I just
thought it was so beautiful
that משה Moshe? knew that השם Hashem had the love for משה
Moshe, to say, this is when you will die. And I think
when you think about it, what an amazing thing to know for
sure with the love of השם Hashem that this is your time.
I was very moved by that. Totally. Yeah. Right. Yep. Okay.
Yeah. Yeah, the אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra has some other discussion on
this. Yeah, okay, we're not going there now. Okay, so it emerges
like this. Okay, now, כמא דאמר רבי יהושע בר אבא אמר רב
גידל אמר רב שמונה פסוקים שבתורה יחיד קורא אותן, Kema de'amar Rabbi
Yehoshua bar Abba amar Rav Gidel amar Rav shemonah pesukim shebaTorah yachid
kore otan, the last שמונה פסוקים shemonah pesukim of the תורה are
read by an
individual. Now what does that mean I'll say in a minute? Who
is that going like?
למימר דלא כרבי שמעון. Lemeimar dela keRabbi Shimon. It's not like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that sounds like
they have a separate status, and, and you know,
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that they were all written by
משה. Moshe, So the גמרא Gemara, says no, אפילו תימא רבי שמעון,
Afilu tima Rabbi Shimon, even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says they
were all written by משה, Moshe הואיל ואשתני אשתני, ho'il ve'ishtani ishtani,
since those שמונה פסוקים shemonah pesukim were still different, they were he
writing about his death which hadn't happened yet and he was writing
it with tears, so they have a separate status. Now what is
this separate status of יחיד קורא אותן? yachid kore otan? So רש״י
Rashi says it means you don't split up that עליה. aliyah. That
עליה, aliyah, those last שמונה פסוקים have to all be one person
takes the, takes the עליה, aliyah, not, you don't split it up
because it has its own special status.
תוספות Tosafot rejects the possibility, says maybe what it means is because
normally we have two people reading. What do you mean two people
reading? The person who gets the עליה aliyah and then the בעל
קורא. ba'al korei. And the person who gets the עליה aliyah is
supposed to sort of also be reading, you know, maybe he reads
it in an undertone or whatever, asks questions, but תוספות says that
can't be what this גמרא Gemara. means. Because in the time of
this גמרא, Gemara there were not two people. There was only one
person. The guy who got the עליה aliyah read. So you know,
so it can't be יחיד yachid means you read without the בעל
קורא ba'al korei because there was no בעל קורא ba'al korei in
the time of the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so, so
the basic, the standard, let me just check if there's another explanation.
One minute.
Okay, this is the word. Okay, so let's keep on going.
What? No, he says like רש״י. Rashi. Okay, now, יהושע כתב ספרו.
והכתיב, Vehaktiv, doesn't it say וימת יהושע בן נון עבד השם? Vayamot
Yehoshua bin Nun eved Hashem?
So you know, it's the same problem in יהושע as we have
in the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. You're writing about your own death.
דאסקיה אלעזר. De'askei Elazar. Fine, אלעזר Elazar finished it up. Okay, that
doesn't bother us so much. We don't have to have a whole
debate about that. Okay, so last פסוקים there. והכתיב ואלעזר בן אהרן
מת. Vehaktiv ve'Elazar bin Aharon met.
But one minute, it's also his death is also inside יהושע.
דאסקיה פנחס. De'askei Pinchas. So פנחס Pinchas finished it. Okay, now שמואל
כתב ספרו. Shmuel katav sifro. Oh, it asks the question. Okay, so
I forgot about that. The גמרא Gemara's asks the question everyone's asking.
והכתיב ושמואל מת. Vehaktiv ve'Shmuel met. Yeah, שמואל א׳. Shmuel Aleph. Right,
שמואל א׳, Shmuel Aleph, that's true. Oh, it's way early. Okay, good
point. And then בעלת אוב. ba'alat ov. Right, right, right, right, right,
right. Fine, the first occurrence of his death. Fine, anyway, three chapters
before it actually ends. Okay, moving on. דאסקיה גד החוזה ונתן הנביא.
De'askei Gad HaChozeh veNatan HaNavi. Fine,
גד Gad and נתן Natan finished it up. Okay. Who's גד החוזה?
Gad HaChozeh? He was one of the נביאים, nevi'im. גד Gad and
נתן. Natan. He was just called חוזה, chozeh, not a נביא. navi.
Okay, now דוד כתב ספר תהלים על ידי עשרה זקנים. David katav
sefer Tehillim al yedei asarah zekenim.
Okay, and again רש״י Rashi lists how those עשרה זקנים asarah zekenim
link up to particular פרקים perakim in תהלים. ולחשוב נמי איתן האזרחי
Ulechshov nami Eitan HaEzrachi
because it says one of them is a מזמור לאיתן האזרחי mizmor
le'Eitan HaEzrachi or whatever the opening is. So the גמרא Gemara says,
well that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. The גמרא Gemara
says אמר רב איתן האזרחי זהו אברהם. Amar Rav Eitan HaEzrachi zehu
Avraham. No, when we said one of them was אברהם, Avraham, we
meant the one that said, you know, דכתיב הכא איתן האזרחי dechativ
hacha Eitan HaEzrachi
which is that פרק perek in תהלים that identifies him, וכתיב התם
מי העיר ממזרח. vechativ hatam mi he'ir mimizrach.
So אזרחי, ezrachi, מזרח, mizrach, right, who is the one that came
from the east? צדק יקראהו לרגלו Tzedek yikra'ehu leraglo and that's assumed
to refer to אברהם, Avraham, אף על פי איתנים, af al pi
Eitanim, the strong ones are referring to the אבות. avot. Okay, now
חשיב משה. chashiv Moshe. Now משה's Moshe. one of the authors of
תהלים. וקחשיב הימן Vekachashiv Heiman and it also mentions הימן Heiman as
presumably somebody else. ואמר רב הימן זה משה. Ve'amar Rav Heiman zeh
Moshe. But doesn't רב say הימן Heiman is משה? Moshe Now that's
talking about a פסוק pasuk in מלכים, Melachim, not a פסוק pasuk
in תהלים that says ויחכם מכל האדם מאיתן
האזרחי vayechkam mikol ha'adam me'Eitan HaEzrachi referring to שלמה. It says שלמה
was wiser even than the איתן האזרחי. Eitan HaEzrachi. So who is
this person that שלמה's being compared to that he was wiser than?
So רב said it means משה. Moshe? Okay, so if the איתן
האזרחי Eitan HaEzrachi there in מלכים Melachim means משה, Moshe. so how
come here in תהלים we've identified משה Moshe. and איתן האזרחי Eitan
HaEzrachi as different authors? So the גמרא Gemara says דכתיב הכא הימן,
dechativ hacha Heiman, how do we know it's משה? Moshe, כתיב הכא
הימן וכתיב התם בכל ביתי נאמן הוא. Kativ hacha Heiman vechativ hatam
bechol beiti ne'eman hu. Okay, so תרי הימן הוו. Trei Heiman havu.
Fine, there were two הימן. Heiman.
There was one that refers to משה, Moshe that's the one in
מלכים. Melachim. There's the הימן Heiman which is in, which is in
תהלים, which is somebody different. Oh, I'm sorry, I said איתן האזרחי
Eitan HaEzrachi before
when I was talking about, I got mixed up. I
excuse myself. I excuse myself. The earlier statement of איתן האזרחי זהו
אברהם Eitan HaEzrachi zehu Avraham was the פסוק pasuk by, excuse me,
ויחכם מכל האדם מאיתן האזרחי, vayechkam mikol ha'adam me'Eitan HaEzrachi, excuse me.
Okay, that was the פסוק pasuk by שלמה. Now this פסוק pasuk
about הימן Heiman is another פסוק pasuk והימן וכלכל veHeiman veChalkol etcetera
and so fine. But the point is
they...
so you know we say that that's so so so we have
identified them as the same. הימן Heiman we say elsewhere is משה,
Moshe. here in a different place in תנ״ך, Tanach, here we say
they're different, so we say that there are two הימנס. Heimans. Fine,
excuse me. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תרי הימן הוו. trei
Heiman havu.
Fine, there's one הימן Heiman that refers to משה Moshe? somewhere else,
but the הימן Heiman here in תהילים Tehillim is somebody other than
משה. Moshe. Now, משה כתב ספרו ופרשת בלעם. Moshe katav sifro u’parshat
Bilam. It's very interesting that we wait for משה Moshe till the
end, like why don't we start with משה? Moshe Maybe we wanted
to get the whole יו״ד? yod? I don't know. Anyway, ואיוב. v’Iyov.
But now the reason really is because now we want to use
this to focus on איוב, Iyov right? So before we were talking
about the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and the last eight פסוקים. Now
we're using it to hone in on the איוב Iyov discussion. What
הימן Heiman
89, 89, that's just before the מזמור mizmor of משה. Moshe? So
there is like almost a... That's an interesting point. That's an interesting
point that the הימן Heiman comes before the מזמור mizmor for the
משה. Moshe, Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's well, maybe and that's
because of that, maybe we wanted to say they were somebody different.
But okay. Now we're going to focus in on איוב. Iyov Now,
מסייע ליה לרבי לוי בר לחמא. msayei lei l’Rabbi Levi bar Lachma.
דאמר רבי לוי בר לחמא, de’amar Rabbi Levi bar Lachma, איוב בימי
משה היה. Iyov bimei Moshe haya. איוב Iyov, was at the time
of משה, Moshe which the גמרא Gemara raised earlier or whatever clearly
said earlier, that has משה Moshe writing it. כתיב הכא ktiv hacha
מי יתן איפו ויכתבון מלי, mi yiten eipo v’yichtevun milai, right? By
איוב, Iyov who will write down my words? וכתיב התם u’chtiv hatam
ובמה יודע איפו. u’vameh yivade eipo. So the איפו איפו eipo eipo
tells you it's משה. Moshe So the גמרא Gemara says give me
a break, there's a lot of איפוs. eipo ואימא בימי יצחק, v’eima
bimei Yitzchak, דכתיב d’chtiv מי איפו הוא הצד ציד. mi eipo hu
hatzad tzayid. ואימא בימי יעקב, v’eima bimei Yaakov, דכתיב d’chtiv אם כן
איפו זאת עשו. im kein eipo zot asu. ואימא בימי יוסף, v’eima
bimei Yosef, דכתיב d’chtiv איפו הם רועים. eipo heim ro’im. A lot
of איפוs eipo in תנ״ך. Tanach. How do you decide to assign
it to משה? Moshe לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka datcha, דכתיב d’chtiv
מי יתן בספר ויוחקו. mi yiten basefer v’yuchaku. At the end of
the פסוק pasuk of מי איפו מי יתן איפו ויכתבון מלי, mi
eipo mi yiten eipo v’yichtevun milai, the end of that פסוק pasuk
is who would put it in a book and they should be
like, you know, engraved. ומשה הוא דאיקרי מחוקק, u’Moshe hu de’ikri mechoquek,
דכתיב d’chtiv וירא ראשית לו כי שם חלקת מחוקק ספון. vayar reishit
lo ki sham chelkat mechoquek safun. The lawgiver, the engraver, the, you
know, carving it into stone. So anyway, so therefore that echoes the
idea of משה. Moshe. So משה Moshe was the one who wrote
it. רבא אמר Rava amar איוב בימי מרגלים היה. Iyov bimei meraglim
haya. It was the time of מרגלים. meraglim. כתיב הכא ktiv hacha
איש היה בארץ עוץ איוב שמו. ish haya b’eretz Utz Iyov shemo.
וכתיב התם u’chtiv hatam היש בה עץ. hayesh bah eitz. So עוץ
Utz and עץ. eitz. So the גמרא Gemara says... Well, I know
that. מי דמי? mi dami? How can you compare? הכא עוץ התם
עץ. hacha Utz hatam eitz. Not the same word. And we know
the גמרא Gemara always is exactly precise about that. So the גמרא
Gemara says הכי קאמר ליה משה לישראל. hachi ka’amar lei Moshe l’Yisrael.
No, it's not just the עוץ Utz עץ, eitz, but there's like
a meaning behind
it. ישנו לאותו אדם ששנותיו ארוכות כעץ והוא מגן על דורו כעץ?
yeshno l’oto adam sheshnotav aruchot k’eitz v’hu magen al doro k’eitz? Maybe
איוב Iyov is still alive? His life
he lives as long as these trees, you know, live hundreds of
years, we’ll see about that in a minute, and he protects them
like a tree and if he's still alive it's going to be
hard for us to conquer the land. So it's not just the
עוץ Utz and עץ, eitz, but the significance of why משה Moshe
was asking about it. Now, it is a good question. What the
heck does the גמרא Gemara mean? How is מרגלים meraglim different than
משה? Moshe, Maybe it's not. Maybe it's a different way of saying
the same point, you know, but just getting to it from a
different פסוק. pasuk. But I also think it's a question of not
just when did he live, right, but sort of like who wrote
it. If you say that משה, Moshe he lived בימי משה bimei
Moshe and it's from a פסוק pasuk of ויכתבון מלי, v’yichtevun milai,
writing my words, right, and משה Moshe, is, you know, the one
who writes and so on, so it sounds like משה Moshe is
actually the author, right, which is what they said before, משה Moshe
is the author of איוב. Iyov If you say he was living
in the time of the מרגלים, meraglim, you're not even talking, you
know, it happens to be when משה was alive, but you're not
even thinking about משה. That's not your context. So then who knows
who the author was? Right? So I don't think it was a
difference of chronology, but it's very different to think about משה writing
it and also the difference also is as the גמרא’s Gemara going
to get to, is whether איוב was true or not, right? Did
it actually happen? It's true, let me say that. Is it historical
or not? Okay, did it actually happen? So if you say that
משה wrote it, right, you can think about it as the ספרי
חכמה sifrei chochma without having to be historical, right, as I said,
you know, because משה, you know, the one who wants to know
about צדיק ורע לו רשע וטוב לו. tzaddik v’ra lo rasha v’tov
lo. If you talk about the time of the מרגלים, meraglim, then
you're thinking about it I think more historically and less as this
like ספר חכמה, sefer chochma, yes. Yeah, no, I'm just going to
say, I wanted to reinforce that first possibility,
it's really powerful
to have משה be the author of איוב, right? He's the נאמן,
ne’eman, the נאמן ביתו. ne’eman beito.
That's a good point too, and it's about questioning God, pure אמונה,
emunah, and at night by candlelight you see you get a glimpse
into his doubt, into his other... Right, right, right.
That's interesting, right. Not just about sort of the wisdom of it,
but that sense of אמונה emunah and the sense about how one
grapples with the issues of אמונה, emunah, absolutely. Yeah. Alright, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, now here we get this idea. יתיב
רבנן קמיה דרבי שמואל בר נחמני ויתיב וקאמר איוב לא היה ולא
נברא. Yativ rabanan kamai de-Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani ve-yativ ve-ka-amar Iyov lo
hayah velo nivra. איוב never existed. אלא משל הוא היה. Ela mashal
hu hayah. It was just a משל, mashal, it's to talk about
this reflection on אמונה emunah and on שכר ועונש. sachar ve-onesh. אמר
ליה עליך אמר קרא, Amar lei alecha amar kra, regarding you the
verse says, איש היה בארץ עוץ איוב שמו. Ish hayah b'eretz Utz
Iyov sh'mo.
How can you say he didn't exist? It says right there, it
gave him a name. So he says, אלא מעתה ולרש אין כל
כי אם כבשה אחת קטנה אשר קנה ויחיה Ela mi-ata u-l'rash ein
kol ki im kivsah achat ktanah asher kanah v'yichyeh etc. So how
about that whole משל, mashal, you know, that's given to דוד about
the poor person and the sheep and whatever? So they say look,
you know, it describes it, you know, I mean obviously it's a
משל. mashal. All right, מיהו? mihu? So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
מי הוה mi hava with that happen happen happen, אלא משל בעלמא
הוה. ela mashal b'alma hava. נמי משל בעלמא. nami mashal b'alma. What
do I care if it uses concrete imagery? It's still a משל.
mashal. No, אם כן שמו ושם עירו למה? im kein sh'mo v'sheim
iro lamah?
Why does it name him and name his city? That obviously shows
we're talking about a real person. Of course you could say no,
it's just to make it more realistic. But anyway, but there you
have actually the possibility that he never existed. But it's rejected. What?
It's rejected by that אמורה, Amora, by רבי שמואל בר נחמני. Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachmani. רבי יהודה ורבי אלעזר דאמרי תרוייהו איוב מעולי גולה
היה. Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Eliezer d'amrei tarvaihu Iyov mei'olei golah hayah.
He returned in the time of the Second בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
right, which also raises the importance, sort of situates it also in
the question about שכר ועונש, sachar ve-onesh, right? You've just lived through
the whole חורבן הבית, churban habayit, you want to understand the justice
of God's ways. If you think about it, right, to some degree,
that's like, you know, the book of, what do you call it,
of איכה, Eicha, right? So there's that questioning of the, yes, injustice.
Where is עוץ? Utz? Where's עוץ? Utz? Yeah, I don't know. In
Oz, he traveled to the Wizard of Oz. Oh really? עוץ Utz
is Oz? Yeah, ארץ עוץ. Eretz Utz.
That's very interesting. Very interesting. Okay. Okay, now מעולי גולה היה ובית
מדרשו בטבריה. mei'olei golah hayah u-vei midrasho b'Tveryah.
Now,
but of course then where did he go? He situated himself after
he came back, he lived in טבריה. Tveryah. I don't know why
it assigns טבריה. Tveryah. טבריה Tveryah was where רבי lived, right? So
it was also very cosmopolitan, right? It was very cosmopolitan, right? Yeah,
after צפורי, Tzipori, I think. So maybe that also has to do
with the, you know, the sort of general wisdom about it, the
philosophical. Okay. היה, Haya, מתיב אשי ימי שנותיו של איוב משעה שנכנסו
ישראל למצרים ועד שיצאו. meiseiv Ashi yemei shnotav shel Iyov mi-sha'ah she-nichnesu
Yisrael l'Mitzrayim v'ad she-yatzu. Now
איוב lived for 210 years, the time for the same time when
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael entered מצרים Mitzrayim ועד שיצאו. v'ad she-yatzu. How
do we know this? Actually this comes from the פסוקים, because it
said that איוב was 70 and then after all this stuff happened
it said at the end of איוב that God doubled his years,
which you could mean like another 70, but it could also read
another 140, twice more than he had. So that's 210. That's the
time period of the Jews in מצרים. Mitzrayim. So the גמרא Gemara
assumes what that means is that that's not just the length he
lived, but the time he lived. He actually lived during the גלות
מצרים, galus Mitzrayim, which by the way is also very nice if
you think about the symbolism. There he is, he's living at the
time, I mean I don't know if we're assuming he's Jewish or
not, but when he said he came up in the time of
the Second בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash we were assuming he's Jewish. I'm
not sure we're assuming he's Jewish right here. The גמרא Gemara is
going to discuss that. But anyway, but there he is, he's living
during the enslave, you know, being enslaved in Egypt. Where is, you
know, the justice in the world? Where is צדק? tzedek? Why are
we enslaved? And so on. I mean he doesn't, but and then
it ends at the time of the redemption when they're exiled, you
know, when they receive גאולה. geulah. So he can live 210 years
and not see where God is and then in the end, you
know, you have the redemption. So that assigns him to the period
of the exile in Egypt. So the גמרא Gemara says, so anyway
but that doesn't fit with the idea that he lived in the
time of the
גלות galus of the חורבן בית המקדש. churban Beit Hamikdash. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אימא כמי שעה שנכנסו ישראל למצרים ועד שיצאו. eima
ki-mi-sha'ah she-nichnesu Yisrael l'Mitzrayim v'ad she-yatzu. No,
he lived 210 years but that wasn't exactly when he lived. Okay,
but again it's very interesting, you know, we read through the גמרא
Gemara. oh he lived here, he lived here, he lived here, he
lived here, right? All of these things, you know, are sort of
are ways of framing what the struggle was, right? משה, צדיק ורע
לו tzaddik v'ra lo as Rabbi Do said also the question of
אמונה. emunah. The מרגלים, meraglim, here it is, you're, you know, what
happens when you're decreed 40 years now to wander in the wilderness,
right? When you were expecting to go in to the land of
Israel for this one sin, doesn't that seem disproportionate? Where's God's justice?
Right? After the חורבן הבית churban habayit and then it ends though
with re-entering the land, right? The exile in מצרים Mitzrayim and it
ends with the redemption, periods where God seems absent or things seem
unjust, you know, and then assigning this to those times. It's really
a commentary, right, about how איוב is relevant for all for so
many different historical times when God seems to not be present and
requires sustaining faith and then ultimately, you know, at least in some
of these cases clear redemption happens. Yes, Jenna. Assuming then that he
was Jewish and living in מצרים? Mitzrayim? Well this הוה אמינא havah
amina which the גמרא Gemara rejects but initially it thought he was
living in מצרים Mitzrayim did not identify whether he was Jewish or
not. Okay. Right, right, right. No, but
I think what I'm reading it as is that in these explanations
it's still a משל, Mashal, but it's a משל Mashal of sort
of of taking the reality of 210 years of exile in Egypt
and where is God and telling that story in the story of
איוב, taking the story of the מרגלים Meraglim and where did God
de- you know whatever and telling that in the איוב story or
the גלות Golus whatever. So right, not to literally right. No, no,
no, no, I'm assuming it means that that's that's the form of
telling the story of that lived experience. Yes. Is there somewhere in
מדרש Midrash about איוב and בלעם Bilam being- Yes,
that's not in this גמרא. Gemara But yes, that's true. Yes, there
is a מדרש about איוב being one of פרעה's Paroh advisors. You're
right, right, I didn't connect those, but that would very much fit
with this, we could have him at this time but not one
of the people that was in the in the enslaved. That's correct.
And there's another piece of that מדרש with משה and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and jumping forward. How can that be? Because of ככה
עלה במחשבה kacha ala b'machshava whatever and it says a word about
that in איוב too of like where were you? This is- Right,
that's true. Right. I mean in general חז"ל Chazal questioning God's justice
occurs in other contexts. That's true. Okay. Am I reading this correctly
that the person who identifies this as a parable, a משל, Mashal,
is anonymous? Correct. Right. Oh, that's interesting too. It's anonymous. Right. Exactly.
Okay, let's read one more sentence about this. מתיבי, Meseivi, I'll ask
you on this: שבעה נביאים נתנבאו לאומות העולם ואלו הן: Shiva nevi'im
nisnabu l'umos ha'olam v'eilu hein: בלעם ואביו, Bilam v'aviv,
why we assume בלעם בן בעור Bilam ben Beor because he was
named, but other people are named also. Anyway, בלעם Bilam and his
father, ואיוב אליפז התימני ובלדד השוחי וצופר הנעמתי ואליהו בן ברכאל, v'Iyov,
Elifaz haTemani, uBildad haShuchi, v'Tzofar haNa'amati, v'Elihu ben Barachel, those are הבוזי,
haBuzi,
those are all איוב's friends there. Okay, so what's the question? The
question is, is that they're אומות העולם, umos ha'olam, and you said
that he came back in the time from the time of the
גלות Golus in בבל, Bavel, which means that he was a Jew,
and this says that he was a non-Jew. Now, by the way,
I have no idea why we are assuming that איוב and his
pals there are נביאים. nevi'im? Like why do we have to assume
that they're נביאים? nevi'im Because their book was written down? But it
was one of the כתובים and anyway, and you know, and how
about- all you need anyway is one author to have רוח הקודש.
ruach hakodesh. You don't need all of- and so I don't even
understand what this
identifying them as נביאים nevi'im. is about. Doesn't it mean though that
like- isn't it weird if someone not Jewish is in the- Yeah,
but
yes, but whether Jewish or not Jewish, a נביא navi or not
נביא, navi, like I don't just see why there's an idea that
they have to- I mean, if you want to say the book
was written by- by איוב, he was the author of it, but
we didn't, we said משה authored it, right? But you know, anyway,
I don't see where in the story they have to be נביאים.
nevi'im. And even if somebody here had to have רוח הקודש, ruach
hakodesh, because you don't have to be a נביא navi to write
כתובים to have to have רוח הקודש, ruach hakodesh, right, I don't
still see why all of them here are assigned נביאים. nevi'im Anyway,
it says so clearly he's clearly he's not Jewish. So the גמרא
Gemara says: ולטעמיך אליהו בן ברכאל לאו מישראל הוה? Uletamecha, Elihu ben
Barachel lav miYisrael hava? Clearly-
so what do you mean? אליהו Elihu clearly was Jewish. And how
do we know clearly he was Jewish? So some say, well, come
on, he's got a name אליהו, Elihu, so clearly I'm serious. Anyway,
the גמרא assumes he was Jewish. So it doesn't say here people
aren't Jewish. והכתיב ממשפחת רם, Vahaksiv mimishpachas Ram, it says from the
family of רם, Ram,
which obviously means like אברהם Avraham is what we're assuming. אלא, so
some of these people were Jewish. So what does it mean that
they were prophets for the non-Jews? אינבואי אינבו לאומות העולם, Inivui inivu
l'umos ha'olam,
they prophesied to the non-Jews. Okay. הכי נמי איוב אינבואי אינבו לאומות
העולם, Hacha nami Iyov, inivui inivu l'umos ha'olam,
he prophesied. Now, of course, why do we assume the prophecy was
directed to the non-Jews? Maybe it was- maybe the book of איוב
was primarily written for non-Jews? How do we know? I mean, it's
a general ספר חכמה, sefer chochmah, but why do we assume it's
specifically for non-Jews? Anyway, so the גמרא says: אטו כולהו נביאי מי
לא אינבו לאומות העולם? Atu kulhu nevi'ei mi lo inivu l'umos ha'olam?
All of the prophets, their prophecy is relevant for non-Jews. התם עיקר
נבואתייהו לישראל, Hasam ikar nevuasaihu l'Yisrael,
no, there it primarily was directed to Jews, non-Jews could also learn.
הכא עיקר נבואתייהו לאומות העולם. Hacha ikar nevuasaihu l'umos ha'olam.
I still don't understand that. What do you mean the עיקר נבואה
ikar nevuah was אומות העולם? umos ha'olam? Is it because- I mean,
איוב is written in universal tones. So I guess it doesn't mean
that it's- it's more for non-Jews than for- than for Jews, but
it means it's fundamentally universal. So איוב is fundamentally universal where the
other נביאים are fundamentally Jewish. Okay, so it's not- well, yeah, I
don't- Okay, we will end here. Okay, to be-